Good morning, church.
It's really good to see all of you together here today,
and especially as we get toward the end of a summer season.
I really hope and pray that all of us have great memories from this summer.
It's definitely been a really full summer.
I know for many people, I've been just hearing from a lot of people,
a lot of different things going on,
and hopefully there are great memories from that.
I know for myself, I had some great memories here with our church family together,
things like serving together side by side early this summer,
as we had like a work day together,
or some of our times just gathering in worship.
I know personally for me,
one great memory that stands out to me
is my wife and I just celebrated our 16th anniversary
a couple weeks ago.
And yeah, it's not a milestone or anything,
but we took a little trip to Vermont together.
That was really fun.
Everything was very green.
Did that while our son was at band camp.
So yeah, it was a great summer
and hopefully we have a great fall season
ahead of us to look forward to.
And especially as we get toward the fall season,
I know a lot of things are gonna change
around Ann Arbor, right?
and a lot of different moving pieces.
Some of you may actually be new to Ann Arbor,
new to the University of Michigan or otherwise here this morning.
If you are new to town, we welcome you.
So glad that you're here to check out our church family this morning
and see what God is doing here.
We hope that you're blessed today
and encouraged through your time together with us.
And I think for all of us, anytime we go into a fall season,
it just feels like a lot of new things,
a lot of new opportunities come our way.
I want to take a moment also to just give a special shout out
to all the leaders serving in our church.
We just had over the last couple of days like a leadership retreat that we do every year to kind of gather together and pray and focus in for the new year.
And I'm really grateful for all the leaders serving in our church in that way that have kind of dedicated their time and energy to that.
But also I know just across our church many people are getting ready for this fall season in all of our ministry teams.
Some of you are here because you're getting ready to be part of Campus Missions Week this coming week, reaching out to all the new students.
And I'm just so thankful for all of that, and especially for some of you who, again, might be new to Ann Arbor.
This is an exciting time to be here, and we hope you have a great time getting settled into this new community.
As we get started here this morning, you know, we're going to be going through kind of a meaningful time in our church as well.
We want to prepare well for this new season.
And so over the next couple of weeks, we're going to be actually kind of revisiting our church's mission and vision that God has given us.
And so if you're a regular part of our church, this will be a good time to kind of review those and kind of get up to date on them.
If you're new to our church, this is actually a really good time to find out about who we are
and about what God's called us to do as a church and how we live out our faith together.
And then after that, on September 13th and three Sundays from now,
we're going to be sharing our annual theme for the year that just helps give some kind of focus and direction
to everything that we do in a given year's ministry.
So those are some things for us to look forward to.
But today, what we're going to do is we're kind of coming to the end of actually a two-year theme
that we've been focused on over the last couple of years.
I think it's been really good for us, but it made me think about like how might we be able to reflect on this
to remember some of the things that God has done and sort of process and move forward from that together.
I don't know if how many of you use something like Google Photos or like Apple Photos or something like that,
but I really like Google Photos because every once in a while, actually it's maybe more than I want it to,
It'll, like, send me a little notification, a little prompt saying, you know, different things.
It'll be like, you know, look back at your cats over the years, and then it'll be like a slideshow of, like, different pictures of my cats.
Or look back at how my son Nicholas has grown up over the years.
You know, I get to see him.
Like, oh, look, he used to be so cute, and now he's a teenager.
You know, and so, you know, all these things, right?
And look back at photos of your wife, or look back at photos of your church over the years.
Got a lot of different things like that.
And it's actually really helpful for me.
Some of you know that I don't really have visual memories.
And so when I look back at that, I'm like, oh, like it helps me kind of revisit that moment
and remember that experience.
And maybe even in different times, remember what God was doing in my life.
And so we want to kind of do that together today as we reflect back on our theme over
the past two years, which if you've been here, you know our theme the past two years
has been deep and wide.
We've been talking about how the deeper our walk with Christ is, the wider our witness
to the world will be.
We've been talking about that over the past two years.
I think it's been really good for our church family to go through that together.
And for those of you who have been with us for the last year or two or so, you've been
part of that and you've seen some of that, and hopefully this will bring back good memories.
And for those of you who are new to our church family here today, checking things out, well,
hopefully this will give you a sense of what God's been doing in our church life and even
what it's like to be part of this church community here.
And so we're going to go ahead and dive into this today.
And I was really wrestling with where to look in Scripture to kind of try to give us some grounding in this.
And I feel like the Lord led me to a passage in Isaiah 54.
And so if you want to open up your Bibles to Isaiah 54 to follow along with us, that would be really great.
We also always have all of our verses up on the screen in front of us.
But it's great to have the Word of God open as we look into it together.
So we're going to look at Isaiah 54, verses 1 through 3.
I'll go ahead and read these verses for us.
Isaiah 54, 1 to 3 says this.
Sing, O barren one who did not bear.
Break forth into singing and cry aloud,
you have not been in labor.
For the children of the desolate one
will be more than the children of her who is married,
says the Lord.
Enlarge the place of your tent
and let the curtains of your habitations be stretched out.
Do not hold back.
Lengthen your cords and strengthen your stakes.
For you will spread abroad to the right and to the left
and your offspring will possess the nations
and will people the desolate cities.
Amen.
Can I pray for us as we've read God's word?
Lord, we invite you into this time
as we look into these holy scriptures.
We thank you for your word that leads us to life,
to salvation, to freedom, to fullness.
Thank you, God, for the gift of your word.
And thank you, God, as well for the gift
of our church community that we can look
into your word together and then respond to it together
and live it out together.
We pray you would guide us in that.
Lord, even as we reflect on what you've been doing
the last couple of years, that you would solidify
those lessons, God, and you would also give us faith to look forward into new things that you
have in store for us. So bless our time together here, Lord. It's in Jesus' name that we pray.
Amen. Amen. So as we look into this passage here together, for some of us, we may be a little
bit unfamiliar with what's going on in Isaiah. What's happening here is that this prophecy is
given through Isaiah to the people of Judah who have been exiled into the empire of Babylon.
and the reason that they are in exile is because they had rebelled against God. They had turned
away from God's commands. They had fallen into idolatry, worshiping other gods. They'd been
unfaithful to their relationship with God, and so God actually brought judgment upon them
for their disobedience by bringing the Babylonian empire to come and carry them away into exile,
where they were for 70 years, and so during that exile, God did not give up on them. God did
not forget them. God did not just abandon them. In fact, God continued to speak to them through
prophets like Isaiah to tell them where to place their hope and how to actually turn back to God
even in the exile that they were in. And so here in this passage, the people are now portrayed as a
barren woman. So the woman here who cannot conceive and cannot have children, she's described as
barren. She's described as desolate. That is a kind of personification of the people of Judah who are
there in exile, the Hebrew people. And for us to kind of understand what's going on here, for in the
ancient Near Eastern times and places, for a woman to be barren and childless was something that had
a lot of practical and social ramifications. Socially, it was a pretty shameful thing. It was
like, oh, you're a woman. Part of your big role in society is actually to get married, to have
children, to raise the next generation. That was important. And for someone not to be able to do
that, that felt very shameful and that had social ramifications for that person. And it was also
practically difficult because for a woman at that time, she would need to have children to help care
for the household, to help take care of the family, and also for that woman as she got older to have
someone who would take care of her. No social security, no Medicaid, no anything like that,
no retirement savings. It's, do you have a family that's going to care for you even in your old age?
And so to portray this woman as barren, as desolate, and to describe God's people that way
in exile really held a, like, it was a very strong visual for the people to be thinking about and to
be reflecting through. And this really was a reflection of the people's relationship with God,
that they had become distant from God.
And because of that, there was this emptiness,
there was this fruitlessness in their relationship with God
who they were supposed to love and serve.
And so this prophecy, as we look at it today,
it actually offers hope that God's plans
for the exiled Hebrews were not finished yet,
and that God actually had plans to fulfill and restore
and redeem them and bring them back out of the exile
that they were currently in.
And so what does God speak to the people
that we can now process through and think about today?
Well, the first thing that God speaks to the people about
is actually to call them to worship in exile.
And this is something, if you think about this,
I mean, it seems kind of wild.
Like, I mean, how many of us,
if somebody said, if we have like the worst day of our life,
like if you fail that exam,
and then if the guy that you like rejects you
and isn't interested in you,
and then something bad happens in your family
and things are falling apart
and then you're going through a financial struggle
and all those things pile up on you at once
and someone comes to you and says,
hey, let's have a party, let's celebrate.
Well, that would feel really weird.
That would feel misplaced.
This is not the time to celebrate, right?
But that's actually exactly what God speaks
to the people here, to worship in their exile.
He specifically says, sing and cry aloud.
And just to make sure we don't understand,
these are not songs of mourning.
This is not cry aloud in pain or in suffering.
Oh, help me.
It's not that.
This is to sing and to sing a joyful song.
To cry aloud is actually a cry of rejoicing, celebration.
It's basically saying, like, this is just not a natural reaction at all for someone in exile,
for this image of a barren woman who can't have the children she so longs for.
This doesn't make any sense at all, and yet this is what God is speaking to the people.
to actually do. And further than that, he actually says, go ahead and sing and cry aloud before the
signs of labor have come. And so before there's even a pregnancy, before that time of labor has
come and the child's about to be born, I think that, you know, from what I understand, labor is
painful. I don't know. I can't speak from experience. Pretty sure, yeah, okay, there we go.
Amen. It's painful. But at least if you have a pregnancy and the baby has grown to full term
and the labor pains have started, at least even if it's painful, there's a sense, okay,
there's going to be a new life born on the other side. That joy is close by. The answer to those
nine months of prayer and of going through all that, it's nearby. And so maybe there's a sense
of anticipated joy there, right? But that's not the case here. The pregnancy hasn't happened yet,
and the labor pains have not come on yet. In fact, there's no sign that anything is going to go that
direction at all. The people of Judah, they have no sign or indication that their exile is about
to end. They just feel stuck. And yet, even before the signs of labor have come, God is still saying,
sing, cry aloud, rejoice, and celebrate, right? Why? We find out at the end of verse 1 it's based
on a promise. It's based on a promise. It says the children of the desolate one will be more than the
children of her who is married. Wow. Somehow, somehow this desolate woman, this barren woman
that is the people of God
somehow is going to have
more children, be more
fruitful, be more abundant
than the one who right now is
married and maybe already having
children. Somehow this is going to come to be.
And I'm just guessing, I mean, for the
Hebrew people, they're sitting
there, they're in exile, they
don't know how this is going to come to an end, they
don't see any end in sight, any hope
for them to be able to go back home and
return to their normal lives and live in
freedom again, they don't see any of that.
How are they supposed to have hope for a fruitful future, as this promise is indicating to them?
And here, I just want us to start to recognize something about the character of God.
See, God is really consistent in his character, and he's really faithful in the way that he works
among his people. It doesn't mean that God always does the exact same thing, but when we look
throughout the pages of Scripture, we start to see that, hmm, it looks like there's a pattern here.
And so for the people here in this passage, they hear this promise, the children of the desolate
one will be more than the children of her who is married. Well, what are they going to start to
think about? And when we look back through the pages of Scripture, I mean, here, let me just share
with you, there are actually seven births to barren women in Scripture. There's all of them.
I'm not going to go through them one by one. But Sarah giving birth to Isaac all the way to
Elizabeth and John the Baptist as the one that's after this. Six of them are before this time.
And so it starts to look like, wow, wait a second. God is saying the children of the desolate one are
going to be more than the children of her who is married? That doesn't make sense. But wait,
let me look on God's history. Let me look at who God is. Let me look at what God does. Let me look
at how God works among his people. And gosh, that promise starts to look like a pattern.
and so maybe when God tells me this and I'm sitting in exile and I have no hope in sight
and I have no no no idea how this is going to come to pass I look back on the history of God
and his people and maybe I start to have a glimmer of hope and so for us as we look at our lives and
what we have been going through again going through this passage we're trying to reflect a little bit
on the last couple of years.
Do you remember, and God works consistently,
do you remember back about a year ago in September,
we started our second year of this deep and wide theme,
and we looked at that passage in Acts 16
where Paul and Silas were thrown into prison?
You guys remember that passage?
And what happened is that they were in this city of Philippi,
and there was a young girl who was demonized,
who was afflicted with this evil spirit.
And Paul and Silas, they cast out the evil spirit,
and because of that, they end up getting thrown into jail.
And remember, we looked at this picture
of this inner prison that they had been thrown into, right?
You can go ahead and throw that picture up there.
And this is an actual prison cell in Philippi.
We don't know if this is the exact one that they were in.
But they were thrown into this inner prison cell.
And this is a place, it was reserved for the worst criminals
that were going to get the worst sentences,
so they knew they were in big trouble.
It's underground, surrounded by three-foot-thick walls,
no chance of escape, no ventilation, nasty, dirty, smelly, because there's no bathroom.
That just goes on the floor. And then where are they sitting? They're sitting on the floor with
their feet in stocks. Pretty gross. And they're down there, and man, their situation looks truly
hopeless, doesn't it? And as we looked at them in that inner prison, we were challenged ourselves,
somewhat allegorically looking at this, to say, what are the inner prisons of our lives,
where we feel trapped, where we feel like we can't get out of this, maybe very similarly to the
people of Judah who are now in exile in Babylon. How exile, prison, what are we going through where
we feel like, man, there's no way out of this. There's no way I can deal with this horrible
situation that I'm in. And what did Paul and Silas do? Well, right there, even though it made no sense
to do it according to their situation. They worshiped. They worshiped. They rejoiced. They
sang praises. They focused on God. They adored him for who he is and for the kinds of things that he
did. And they did that not because they actually had a greater promise to hope in as well. And the
promise that they hoped in was not a promise that God was going to get them out of jail. That was
not the promise from God. The promise that they had was actually what Jesus had done for them
to save them from their sins,
to give them an eternal hope,
an eternal salvation
that they could always hold onto
that would never be taken away from them.
That was what they held onto in that prison cell.
That was how they were able to rejoice
just as the people in exile
because of the promise of God
that he would redeem and restore
were also called to rejoice.
I love these pictures that we see in Scripture
because they show us this is who God is
and this is how God works.
And by the way, when we look at this story
in Isaiah 54, we hear this prophecy, we see all of that. We have to realize this is not made in
isolation. If you have a paper Bible and maybe you're flipping back and forth, or even if you
take a second and just kind of click backward in your app one chapter, you'll see what's right
before this is Isaiah 53. And if you're familiar with that passage in Isaiah 53, you know that that
was the last of Isaiah's great servant songs. The story of the suffering servant who would take the
sins of the people upon himself. Let me read you a few verses of that. Isaiah 53, 4-6, it says,
Surely he has borne our griefs and carried our sorrows, yet we esteemed him stricken, smitten
by God, and afflicted. But he was pierced for our transgressions, he was crushed for our iniquities.
Upon him was the chastisement that brought us peace, and with his wounds we are healed. All we
like sheep have gone astray, we have turned everyone to his own way, and the Lord has laid
on him the iniquity of us all. See, right before this, again, what reason do the people have to
celebrate? What reason do they have to rejoice? God has just told them what his plan is, that he is
going to send his servant, who is going to actually take the affliction and the sin and the iniquity
of the people upon himself. Isaiah is announcing 700 years beforehand what Jesus would come to do
when he died on the cross to take our sins upon himself.
God is saying, I'm going to redeem you.
I'm going to save you.
I'm going to forgive you.
I'm going to lead you to salvation.
This is the promise.
This is the hope that you can root and ground yourself in.
And so when we look at this, we see, wow, God,
this is the hope that you gave to the people of Judah.
God, this is the hope that you give to us today.
The question we can start to reflect on and consider is for ourselves.
have we also learned to worship in exile? Have we learned to worship in those inner prisons of
our lives where we struggle deeply with things that seem too big for us? I think the only way
that we can do that is if we place our hope in the promise of redemption in Jesus Christ,
this message of the gospel that we believe in and that we hope in. And so as I think about that
and how God's been working in our church the last couple of years, I feel like God just brought me
back to reflecting on some different moments of just seeing people in our church where they grasp
the gospel message at a deeper level. I don't know how many of you may remember Pastor Paul Kim came
as our guest speaker for a refresh weekend back in January 2025. So that's about a year and a half
ago. And when Pastor Paul came, do you guys remember there was this kind of phrase or this
idea he shared with us, don't row the boat but raise the sails. You guys remember that? Right?
And so some of you, maybe you don't.
It's okay, I'll explain it real quick here.
Pastor Paul shared with us, so many of us,
we try to go through life or even relationship with God
or face our struggles or overcome our sins or whatever.
And for many of us, we take the approach of rowing a boat.
So you kind of imagine that and picture,
yeah, thanks, oh, okay, cool, yeah.
So many of us, we take the approach of we're rowing a boat.
Right, and it's like, okay, I need to exert all this effort.
I need to work hard at those oars.
Like some of you, you're actually on crew or have been on crew before.
Some of you, you haven't do that, but you have one of those things called at home
that you do that with, the rowing machine.
Yeah, some of you have a rowing machine.
You know, that's hard work.
You do it the first couple times, you're like, oh, this is easy.
Five minutes later, you're like, oh, my gosh, this is hard.
This is a hard workout.
And imagine these people in exile in Babylon.
You've got to row the boat out of exile.
man
am I going to row my boat across a desert
these are people
they don't have anything
to depend on, their own strength is not going to be
nearly enough
just like for us
when we face our own sins
the wounds in our hearts
that we don't know how to overcome
things we feel enslaved to
it's like man, my effort isn't enough
if my effort was enough, I'd be out of this
already
and so I feel like I have to row this boat
but Pastor Paul shared with us
the gospel isn't about rowing the boat
and you using your own effort
to get to the other side
the gospel is like raising the sails
we raise the sails
and we catch the power of God
the grace of God
and it's the grace of God
that actually carries us
across the lake to the other side
do you remember that?
so as we think about these things
have we spent the last year and a half since then
Have we been just rowing the boat really hard,
feeling stuck, feeling like, oh my gosh,
the wind is against me.
The storm came, like the storm last night
that, thank God, didn't make our building collapse.
Like, the storms come, and the winds and the waves,
they're there, and man, I can't row my way through this.
But God's saying, no, raise the sails.
Raise the sails.
Catch the power of my grace and my mercy
and see where I will carry you to.
And so we're learning,
this is what the gospel message is about,
and then learning to apply that to our lives.
Like shortly after that,
we started using this Two Trees tool.
Do you guys remember that?
By the way, that's still available if you wanna go.
HMCC.tech slash Two Trees.
You can go and still use that.
We'll leave those things available for us.
And this is from a book by Paul Tripp,
but we used this tool to say,
how do I actually apply the message of the gospel
to different areas of my life?
So if I'm angry with my kids
because they disrespected me,
if I'm frustrated with my classmate
because they didn't do their part of the group project.
If I'm angry at my roommate
because they didn't do the dishes.
If I'm frustrated with my brother and my sister
because they insulted me, whatever.
Like how do we react
and how do we process those experiences
through the lens of the gospel
so the gospel isn't just something
that's about our eternity
but actually affects our life in the here and now.
We're learning to live in that promise,
live in that truth, right?
How have we been responding to that,
living that out now as we've gone through
these couple years of deep and wide. I think when we learn to root our lives in the gospel,
we can have this joyful hope. Even in the face of difficulty, we can trust that God
is going to lead us through breakthroughs, freedom, salvation, healing. He's going to bring
us out of that prison, out of that exile. We need to learn to really fix our hope on the gospel of
Jesus Christ. Amen? Turn to someone next to you and say, hope in Jesus Christ. Okay? So in this
first verse, this is what it's all about. It's like, okay, let's learn to worship. Let's learn to
find hope in that promise, in the midst of that exile, that prison that we're in. But then verse
two goes on, and we hear we're called to enlarge our tent, right? Now, what's all of this about?
Today, we tend to think of a tent as like just kind of like roughing it out in the desert
somewhere. Maybe we think of like a Eureka tent or something. It's like green and gray, and it's
got those fiberglass poles, right? That's the only tent that we're really familiar with. But here in
this passage, it says, okay, enlarge your tent, let your curtains be stretched out. What's this
talking about? I don't have curtains in my tent. Well, here, let me just give you a couple
visuals to understand this. This is what a tent looks like in the Near Eastern world, still today.
This is like a normal, regular old tent that a person with maybe a small family would have and
would live in out in the desert. It's small, maybe it has like a couple small rooms with like a
curtain to divide those rooms, and you can live there with a small number of people. I've been
in tents like this before, and it's cozy, nice. Okay, a family, a small family can live there
together. But here, the author is saying, no, enlarge your tent. Stretch out the curtains.
What's he talking about? Well, in the Near East, they also, this isn't the only kind of tent they
have. They also have really big tents that look like this one. Okay, in this, if you look at it,
you can see those little spots there. Those are little people right there underneath this big,
expansive tent. The tent material, the curtains, all that is stretched out really wide. It becomes
this huge structure in the desert. And now you can't just fit a couple people under there. You
can actually fit a ton of people under these really huge tents. And again, for us, we tend
to think of tents as kind of roughing it out in the desert. But for families that have these huge
tents, a lot of times the inside is actually really nice and comfortable. This is more modern,
but here, look, they've got couches everywhere for people to lay out on, colorful pillows.
You can just rest your head. Imagine yourself eating grapes, drinking wine or grape juice or
something, right, and there, and just enjoying your hummus and your pita. Like, it's, man,
how nice, right? What a beautiful place to be. And this is the imagery. This is what these kinds
of ideas and thoughts would mean to the people when they hear, enlarge your tent, stretch out
the curtains. And I love it here in this passage. God tells the people, don't hold back. What he
means by this, make it as big as possible. Don't hold back. Don't constrain it to just making a
little addition to your tent, adding a little section to the side of your tent. No, he says,
don't hold back. Make it as big as possible. Why? Because God wanted to bring in so many more people
than they possibly could have expected. And this, again, God is consistent in all of his ways.
Rewind back to God's promise to Abraham.
In Genesis, Genesis 22, 17,
I will surely bless you
and I will surely multiply your offspring
as the stars of heaven
and as the sand that is on the seashore.
This has always been God's plan.
God from Abraham and Sarah, a barren woman,
says I'm gonna give you the nation,
I'm gonna make you a blessing to the nations.
Nations will come from you.
Enlarge your tent,
stretch it out much bigger than you could have thought possible. And along with that, he says,
lengthen your cords and strengthen your stakes. What does that mean? That's literally saying you
need to go deep and wide. That's literally what that is saying. To expand the tent, you're going
to need to stretch out those cords really wide. They're going to need to hold and support all that
fabric, all that material to cover all the people that are going to come into your tent and be part
of your gathering, part of your family. And if you're going to stretch out those cords really wide
and you're going to have this huge tent that by itself, the fabric, the weight of that fabric is
really huge. And then you're going to have desert winds come and blow across. Sometimes gill force
winds in the desert at night, they're going to come against that tent. And so you're going to
need something really strong to hold that tent in place. And so those stakes are going to need to
be driven really deep. Like I obviously don't have any pictures from like long ago of that, but like
here's a little long ago, but see these guys, they're driving in this enormous stake into the
ground. And it requires actually multiple people with sledgehammers to drive in this tent stake
because that tent stake has to be like really strong, thick. It's going to have to go deep into
the ground, right? All to be able to hold the weight and the pressure of that tent that's meant
to cover all of these people. It needs to go very deep to have that strength. And so when we think
about this. And for myself, I think I've just been very blessed over the past couple of years seeing
our church fight to go deeper with God. It's been such a blessing because that depth is going to be
required to be strong, to be able to live out God's purpose and calling for our lives. That's looked a
lot of different ways. I don't know if you remember when we started Deep and Wide as a theme, we
shared this idea of spiritual surface tension, right? Kind of like if you're, you know, many of
us familiar with surface tension, like this paper clip on the top of the water, right? It's
It just sits there because of the surface tension.
And we talked about this idea of spiritual surface tension that keeps us from going into
those deeper areas that maybe we're afraid of, maybe we feel like are too big for us.
It's the inner prison stuff.
It's the exile stuff.
It's the stuff that we can't row our way across.
That spiritual surface tension keeps us from going there.
And we talked about that all throughout this past couple of years.
but I've been so thankful to see our church take on that challenge and say, yes, we're going to go
deeper. And some of that has been through just regular daily stuff. Like about a year and a half
ago, we made like a big push to restart our Bible reading program that we have as a church back in
January 2015, I guess that was. And I've been so grateful. Like I don't know how many people in
our church have come up to me and told me that this is the most consistent they've ever been in
reading the Bible every day. And I'm just like, wow, thank God. And I know we probably have a long
way to go, and sometimes we kind of fall off. We may forget for a few days. We get behind.
But let's not give up on that, because as we make those choices daily to grow in our relationship
with God, it starts to push through that spiritual surface tension to get to those deeper areas.
And on top of that, then there are bigger things that we've gone through together as a church,
as well as personally through just things God leads us through. But just going through our
One Desire fast together. Or even some of you remember our congregational retreat back this
January. We had this theme of make room, right? Making room to go deeper with God, to seek God.
And I remember coming in on Saturday night and taking this picture. And I think most of you are
aware Friday night of that retreat was when my mom passed away. And so I and my family, we left for
quite a while on Saturday and came back in the evening. And this is what we came back to. I took
this picture right when I came in the door. And it was just such a beautiful sight to me to come back
in being like a pretty deep place myself with just, you know, facing the loss of my mom and
having to process all of that. But I just knew, where do I want to be? I want to be with my
spiritual family. I want to be with the people of God. I want to be with people who are focusing
their eyes on the Lord. I want to be with people who are praying together. I want to be with people
who are going deeper with God, because that's what I needed to be part of. And it was such a joy,
even in the midst of that sorrow and that grieving and processing all of that, it was such a joy
to see our church making that space and going deeper with God, and then even taking further
steps, like people doing freedom class and just, you know, digging in to these deeper areas of
life. It's been a joy to see our church do that over this past year. But, you know, along with
all of that deeper growth, there was this conviction that, at least for me personally, that I went into
this theme with. Because my heart, and many of you know, I didn't grow up in the church. I didn't
grow up in the Christian faith. And I think coming from that background, the constant thing that's on
my heart is wanting people who don't know Jesus to hear the gospel for themselves. Wanting the
nations to come to know Christ. Wanting people who are lost, who are far from God, who are hurting,
who are looking for something to hear the gospel message.
And I just felt like God was telling me
to go into this two-year theme of deep and wide,
say, if we really focus on going deeper with God,
then we will become wider witnesses to the world.
And it's been a joy to see that as well,
brothers and sisters, in so many ways.
I mean, over the past couple of years,
we actually formed our outreach team as a church.
Just so you know, that wasn't my idea.
That wasn't our elders' idea.
That was people in our church saying,
we have a heart to reach out and serve.
how can we do this together?
We said, okay, yeah, let's get it started.
Let's set it up.
That was God's work in the church.
And it's been so cool
as those things have started happening,
just seeing people in our church
starting to serve at St. Andrews,
starting to serve at Purple House,
other opportunities as well,
just saying we want to go out
and be messengers and representatives
of the love of God
out into our church community
and doing that in so many ways,
not just through outreach team activities,
but I know many of you
who are college students,
you're just going out on campus
regularly through the school year,
connecting with students, building relationships, trying to share the hope that you have in Christ
with them. I just see God doing that. Even people wanting to participate in missions and go to the
nations or go to places like Chicago and Minneapolis and all of that, and just wanting to be part of
the work that God is doing in the world. I didn't feel, as a pastor, I didn't feel like I had to try
to like twist people's arms to get those things to happen. As people were just growing in their faith,
God was doing that work within us. You know, such a joy to see. And with all of that, just seeing
new people come into our church family all the time. Every Sunday, all of our life groups,
just seeing people come in and experiencing the love of God together with us. I felt like that
picture of deep and wide really came to reality as we actually enlarged our tent together through
all of that process. Through all of this, the passage comes to an end saying, your offspring
will possess the nations. Your offspring will possess the nations. And that by itself, man,
think about the reality of where these people are again. These people are still in exile with no end
in sight. Your offspring will possess the nations. Right now, literally, they're possessed by the
nations. They're in Babylon. They are not free to leave. They're not free to go wherever they want
to. By the way, they have no army. They have no resources. They have no command structure.
They have no anything that would help them to actually take possession of the nations around
them. They have nothing like that. This is like a hopeless suggestion. It's something that could
only be proposed by faith. And I think for some of us, maybe we actually feel ourselves in the same
situation, and that can feel a little overwhelming. Some of us, maybe some of you here, you're college
students, and you're wanting to live out your faith on campus. Maybe you're here because you're
helping lead a life group, or you're here because you're here for Campus Missions Week, and you want
to reach out to students on campus, and maybe that just feels overwhelming. Like, wow, with us and
other churches and other Christian ministries on campus, it just feels like we're so few
to reach the tens of thousands of students and faculty and staff and everybody here that
don't know Jesus. That just feels so overwhelming. Or for others of us, maybe it's we go to our
workplace, we live life in our neighborhoods, meeting our neighbors, we go to our schools and
our kids' classrooms, and we wonder, man, how are we possibly going to share the gospel with all of
these people. But this is what God is telling us to look to as a promise. This trust that God,
just as he is able to bring pregnancy and birth to barren women throughout history, he's able
to bring the nations to know him. He is able to fulfill his promise. And as we look ahead,
for us, we need to be challenged. How can we commit to continuing to go deeper and wider
together because we trust in this promise of God. Your offspring will possess the nations.
What my prayer is, as we reflect on all of this and as we look ahead, is let's really try to
solidify some of those lessons that we've personally learned from this last couple years
of deep and wide. And let's resolve to make that not just a two-year catchphrase, but actually
something that's part of who we are personally and part of what our church culture looks like,
that we are people who go deeper in our relationship with God. And through that,
we are people who go wider in our witness out to the world around us. And so as we close out
this time here today and even look ahead into a new season, can I challenge us with a couple
specific things? Just how can we live in the promise that God has for us? What does that look
like? And a couple practical things that I want to encourage you with is, number one, can we be
people who worship rooted in the gospel? Let's make that the way that we worship together. And I
think this is a big challenge. I loved our opening worship time together this morning. It was such a
joy, declaring the worthiness of God.
And I pray that we can continue that throughout the year.
And what's so important there, and we've talked about that over the summer as we've
gone through like our Bible short series and stuff, which has also been really fun, really
great to go through.
One of the things we've talked about at different points in that series is that we want to
be people who worship not based on our situation and our circumstance, but worship based on
who God is and the promises he's made to us.
That's the kind of worship that we want to have.
And I pray that we'll be a church that grows in that kind of worship because our worship
really reflects our hope, and God is worthy of that worship, and that worship is part of how
we're going to go deeper with God, and how we're going to see more freedom in our lives as we
worship even in exile and in those inner prisons, but along with that, it's also part of our witness
to the world, and I don't know about you, but when people come in and visit us, and we're going to
have probably hundreds of people visit us over the next couple of months here in our church,
when people come in, and they see even the way that we worship, I pray that they will see
not worship based on circumstance like oh man Michigan football team lost their first game oh
my gosh we lost to a horrible team like man okay I don't feel like I can worship now right like I
think that would deeply affect many of us I'd have to fight through that you know stuff like that
our circumstances it affects us man I'm struggling with I'm placed in my dorm room with my roommate
my dorm room feels like an inner prison it's so dank and nasty like my roommate doesn't clean up
like, oh my gosh, can I still worship?
Can I still worship, right?
Or is it just like only when things are going well
we can worship?
Can we be a people that worship
based on the promise of God,
based on the gospel message that's been given to us,
the hope that we have in Christ?
And so regardless of the circumstance
and maybe even more when we're in a dark place,
maybe even more when life is difficult,
that we worship with all of our hearts,
with all the breath that is within us
because God is worthy of that
because that's the hope that we have
and that's the hope that we want to share with the world.
Okay, turn to somebody next to you and say,
worship like that.
Second thing I want to encourage us to do
is just to continue to go deeper with God.
I think for many of us,
we're still just trying to break
that spiritual surface tension.
And I have a feeling that for many of us,
there are some things that God actually brought
to your attention over the last couple years,
and maybe you initially started to respond to God,
you initially started to maybe pray about that,
dig into that, seek even accountability
or prayer from others for that,
but somewhere along the way, it just kind of fell off, and your attention got drawn to something
else. Maybe God is bringing this up today to remind you and to encourage you, don't give up on
that, because there are probably things in all of our lives here. All of us need more of the grace
of God, and maybe for some of us, it's just struggling with pride or self-sufficiency.
For some of us, maybe it's a deep wound in our heart that needs to be healed. For some of us,
maybe it's an addiction that we need to seek freedom from. Can we keep going deeper with God
and say, God, I'm gonna dig into that in prayer once again.
God, I'm going to ask others to pray for me for that again.
God, I'm gonna take steps of faith
and freedom in that direction again.
Can we keep going deeper
and not let that be something we just leave
in the past over these last couple of years?
So recommitting to a deeper devotional life,
recommitting to even pursuing healing and freedom
together as a biblical community together.
That's what we wanna do together as a church.
And then lastly, thirdly here is just,
let's enlarge our tent.
let's really see that as why we're here okay I think it's a great privilege to serve God
here where we are I think it's an amazing thing that we as a church and we as people we get to be
here in a place like Ann Arbor in a place like on this campus where God literally brings the
nations from all over the world over a hundred nations represented here in our community and on
this campus people coming from all over the place from all different backgrounds and walks of life
and the next generation comes here,
whether for college or the next generation
growing up here through our schools
and in our neighborhoods
and being raised within our families
and the neighbors around us
that we reach out to
are literally the future world leaders
that are gonna make a difference in the world.
Like, I think it's such an amazing thing
that we get to be here
and I wanna encourage all of us to embrace that.
For those of us who are maybe
even part of our campus ministry,
go for that this next couple of weeks,
especially as there's so many new people
just looking for connection,
maybe looking for a spiritual home, maybe running away from God, but God's trying to get a hold of
them. Let's believe in that and say, we're going to enlarge our tent to welcome all those people
into our spiritual family. But I'll also just share, for many of us here, where this is our
home, like we're raising our families here, we're working here in this community, and maybe like,
man, it's like, okay, all the noose didn't move in. I was just talking to my wife about this. She
was like, when do I need to avoid campus? Because, yeah, it's just like so much traffic, people
parked over the side of the curb, people driving the wrong way up the one-way street, right? It's
going to be chaos over the next couple of weeks. But even for those of us who are maybe a little
bit older, different stage of life, we're here for a reason too. I don't know how many people
over the years have come into our church, like as a college student, and said, you know what,
it's so great to see families raising their kids in this church. It's so great to have older people
I could look up to in this church. All of us are called to be part of that work of enlarging this
tent. Whether it's for our neighbors, the nations, the next generation coming after us, let's commit
and do that and live that out together. And so as a one thing to close with here today is just to
worship in faith and enlarge our tent for the nations. Worship in faith and enlarge our tent
for the nations. I think God has been really growing us and preparing us over the next couple
of years to keep moving forward in the calling he has for us. As I mentioned, in the next couple
weeks, we're going to talk about our mission and vision that God's called us to together as a
church. We're going to talk about the theme that we're going to be focusing on as we look forward.
I'm so looking forward to that. I'm excited for what God is doing in our church. And I know God
has been preparing many of us here already over these last couple of years for what he has in
store for us. Can we look ahead with eyes of faith? Say, God, we're going to worship you
just based on your promise. Not because we see it yet, not because it makes sense to us,
not because we feel like we can row our boats to it, but God, we're going to raise those sails.
God, we're gonna look to the promise that you have,
that you want your people
to bring the nations home into that tent.
God, you wanna see more people being set free
and brought to salvation and healing,
their lives transformed by the gospel
so they can then go and transform the world.
God, we get to be a part of that.
It's a privilege, it's a joy, it's an honor.
And yeah, sometimes we get tired.
And sometimes there's even discouragement
or struggle along the path.
But God, help us to keep raising those sails,
to keep going deeper,
to keep reaching out to the nations together.